<section id="nxtsearchgui">
      <title>The NXT Search GUI</title>

<para>

The search GUI can be reached either by using <filename>search.bat/search.sh</filename> and
specifying which corpus to load or by using the <filename class="extension">.bat/.sh</filename> for the
specific corpus (if it exists) and choosing the <guimenuitem>Search</guimenuitem> option.  It
has two tabbed windows.  The query tab allows the user to type in a
query.  Cut and paste from other applications works with this
window.  The query can also be saved on the <guimenu>Bookmark</guimenu> menu, but at
May 2004 this doesn't work well for long queries. 
There is a button to press to do the <guibutton>search</guibutton>, which
automatically takes the user either to a pop-up window with an
error message explaining where the syntax of the query is incorrect,
or, for a valid query, to the result tab.  This window shows the
results as an XML tree structure, with more information about the
element the user has selected (with the mouse) displayed below the
main tree.  

</para>
<para>

The GUI includes an option to <guimenuitem>save</guimenuitem> the XML result tree to
a file.  This can be very handy in conjunction with <function>knit</function> 
 for performing data analysis.  It also includes an option
to save the results in a rudimentary <application>Excel</application> spreadsheet.  This is less
handy, especially in the case of complex queries, because the return
value is hierarchically structured  but the spreadsheet
just contains information about each matched element dumped into
a flat list by performing a depth-first, left-to-right traversal of
the results. However, for relatively simple queries and people who are used to
data filtering and pivot tables in <application>Excel</application>, it can be the easiest first
step for analysis.

</para>

<para>

The search GUI works on an entire corpus at once.  This can make
it slow to respond if the corpus is very large or if the query is
very complicated (although of course it's possible to comment out
observations in the metadata to reduce the amount of information it
loads).  Sometimes a query is slow because it's doing something more
complicated than what the user intended.  A query can be interrupted
mid-processing and will still return a partial result list, which 
can be useful for checking it.

</para>

<para>

At May 2004, when the user chooses to open a corpus from the <guimenu>File</guimenu>
menu, the search GUI expects the metadata
file to be called <filename><replaceable>something</replaceable>.corpus</filename>, although many users are likely
to have it called <filename><replaceable>something</replaceable>.xml</filename> (so that it behaves properly in
other applications like web browsers).  Choose the
<guimenuitem>All files</guimenuitem> option (towards the bottom of the open dialogue box) in
order to see <filename class="extension">.xml</filename> files as well as <filename class="extension">.corpus</filename> ones.  

</para>

</section>