<section id="NOM-impl">
   <title id="nom-impl.title">The NITE Object Model</title>

<remark> should NOM come before Data Set Model or after? </remark>
   <para>
The NITE Object Model consists of a general graph structure, and then
some properties imposed on top of that graph structure that make using
that structure more computationally tractable whilst still expressing
the sorts of relationships that are prevalent among annotations.
   </para>

   <para>
The NITE Object Model is a graph where the nodes are required to have
a <firstterm>simple type</firstterm> and may additionally have
<firstterm>attribute-value pairs</firstterm> elaborating on the simple type,
<firstterm>timings</firstterm>, 
<firstterm>children</firstterm> that the node structurally dominates, 
<firstterm>textual content</firstterm>,
<firstterm>pointers</firstterm> relating the node to other nodes,
and <firstterm>external pointers</firstterm> relating the node to external
data not represented in the NITE Object Model.
Any individual node may have either children or textual content, but not
both.  
   </para>

<remark> TEMP do we want to restrict the NOM by definition so that only one external pointer can be included in any node?  This is the de facto restriction in the way external-reference-layers are defined, but the NOM is often less restricted than the layer structure, and it makes sense to me to keep the structure as parallel to pointers as possible (including keeping the arity open). </remark>
<para>
  The <firstterm>simple type</firstterm> is a string.  
</para>

<para>
An <firstterm>attribute</firstterm> is identified by a simple label string and
takes a <firstterm>value</firstterm> that conforms to one of three types: a
string, a number, or an enumeration.  The simple type of the element
determines what attributes it can contain.  For any element, the
simple type plus the attribute-value pairs defined for the element
represent its full type.
</para>

<para>
<firstterm>Timing</firstterm> information can be present, and is represented by
reserved start and end attributes containing numbers that represent
offsets from the start of the synchronized signals.
</para>

<para>
The <firstterm>children</firstterm> are represented by an (ordered) list of other nodes.
</para>

<para>
The <firstterm>textual content</firstterm> is a string.  For nodes that have
children instead of textual content, some NXT-based tools use
an informal convention that the textual content of the node is
equivalent to textual content of its descendants, concatenated
in order and whitespace-separated.
</para>

<para>
The <firstterm>pointers</firstterm> are represented by a list of
<firstterm>role</firstterm> and <firstterm>filler</firstterm> pairs.
A <firstterm>role</firstterm> is a simple label string that has an
expected arity, or number of nodes, expected to fill the role: one, or
one-or-more.  A role is <firstterm>filled</firstterm> by a set of
nodes with the expected arity.  We sometimes use the term
<firstterm>features</firstterm> for these pointers.
</para>

<para>
The <firstterm>external pointers</firstterm> are also represented by a
list of <firstterm>role</firstterm> and <firstterm>filler</firstterm>
pairs.  A <firstterm>role</firstterm> is again a simple label string
with an expected arity of one or one-or-more.
The role of an external pointer
is <firstterm>filled</firstterm> by a string that specifies a datum in
the external reference format, with the details of how the referencing
works left to the application program.  This can be useful, for instance,
in tailored applications that need to cooperate with existing tools that
display data in the other format.
</para>

<para>
The object model also imposes some properties on the parent-child
relationships within this general graph structure.  Firstly, the
parent-child relationships in this graph must be acyclic, so that its
transitive closure can be interpreted as a dominance
relation. Secondly, there must not be more than one path between any
two elements. Because of these constraints, the parent-child graph
(which, unlike a tree, allows children to have multiple parents)
decomposes into a collection of intersecting tree-like structures,
called <firstterm>hierarchies</firstterm>. Each hierarchy has its own structural
ordering (similar to an ordered tree), but these orderings must be
consistent where hierarchies intersect.
</para>

<para>
If an element has timing information, the element's start time must be
less than or equal to its end time. In addition, if elements in a
dominance relation both have timing information, the time interval
associated with the ancestor must include that of the descendant.  The
times of elements need not be consistent with any of the structural
orderings.  Timing information can thus be used to define an
additional partial ordering on the graph, which is not restricted to a
single hierarchy.
</para>

<para>
In the object model, there are no structural or timing constraints
imposed on nodes based on the pointers between them.  The pointers
merely provide additional, arbitrary graph structure over the top
of the intersecting hierarchy model.
</para>

<remark> TEMP We say nodes can have text or children, not both, and that text content of non-leaves is concatenation of descendent's text as informal convention in some tools - is this correct? </remark>

</section>

<!--**************************-->

<section id="layering" xreflabel="NITE Data Set Model">
   <title>The NITE Data Set Model</title>


   <para>
Our object model is simply an abstract graph structure with a number
of properties enforced on it that govern orderings. However, it can be
difficult for data set designers to think of their data in terms this
abstract, rather than the more usual concepts such as corpus, signal,
and annotation.  
For this reason, we provide a data
set model in these familiar terms that can easily be expressed using
our object model and from whose structure the essential properties we
require regarding orderings and acyclicity fall out.  Data set
designers use this level of the model to describe their designs,
and by providing metadata that expresses the design formally, make it
possible to validate the overall structure of any specific data set
against their intended design.
   </para>

<para>
Here we describe the main entities and relationships that occur in
our data set model.
</para>

<variablelist>
   <title>Data Set Model Concepts</title>
<varlistentry>
   <term>Observation</term>
   <listitem><para> 
   An observation is the data collected for one
   interaction — one dialogue or small group discussion, for example.
   </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
   <term>Corpus</term>
   <listitem><para> 
    A corpus is a set of observations that have the
   same basic structure and together are designed to address some
   research need.  For each simple data type, metadata for the corpus
   determines what attribute-value pairs can be used to refine the
   type, whether or not elements of that type have timing information
   and/or children, and what features can be present for them.
   </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>


<varlistentry>
   <term>Agent and Interaction</term>
   <listitem><para> An agent is one interactant in an observation.
   Agents can be human or artificial.  We provide the concept of agent
   so that signals and annotations can be identified as recording or
   describing the behaviour of a single agent or of the interacting
   group as a whole.  As an example, individual agents speak, but it
   takes two of them to have a handshake, and possibly the entire set
   to perform a quadrille.  Any signal or annotation involving more
   than an individual agent counts as belonging to the interaction even
   if it involves a subset of the agents present.
  </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
   <term>Signal</term>
   <listitem><para> A signal is the output from one sensor used to
   record an observation: for example, an audio or video file or blood
   pressure data.  An observation may be recorded using more than one
   signal, but these are assumed to be synchronized, so that
   timestamps refer to the same time on all of them. 
   This can be achieved through pre-editing.  
   Individual signals
   can capture either one agent (for instance, a lapel microphone or  
   a close-up camera) or the interaction among the agents (for instance,
   a far-field microphone or overhead camera).
   </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
   <term id="layer" xreflabel="layer definition">Layer</term>

   <listitem><para> A layer is a set of nodes that together span an
   observation in some way, containing all of the annotations for a
   particular agent or for the interaction as a whole that are either
   of the same type or drawn from a set of related types. Which data
   types belong together in a layer is defined by the corpus metadata.
   For instance, the TEI defines a set of tags for representing words,
   silences, noises, and a few other phenomena, which together span a
   text and make up the orthographic transcription.  In this
   treatment, these tags would form a layer in our data set model.
   </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
   <term>Time-aligned layer</term>
   <listitem><para> 
A time-aligned layer is a layer that contains nodes timed directly
against signal.
   </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
   <term>Structural layer</term>
   <listitem><para> 

A structural layer is a layer where the nodes have children.  
The children of a structural layer are
constrained to be drawn from a single layer, which, in order to allow
recursive structures, can be itself.  Ordinarily
nodes in this layer will inherit timing information from their children
if their children are timed, but this inheritance can be blocked.
   </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
   <term>Featural layer</term>
   <listitem><para> 

A featural layer is a layer where the nodes point to other nodes, but
do not contain children or timing information.  
A featural layer draws together other nodes into
clusters that represent phenomena that do not adhere to our timing
relationships.  For instance, a featural layer might contain
annotations that pair deictic gestures with deictic pronouns.  Since
deictic pronouns and their accompanying gestures can lag each other by
arbitrary amounts, there is no sense in which the deictic pair spans
from the start of one to the end of the other.
   </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
 
<varlistentry>
   <term>External reference layer</term>
   <listitem><para> 

External reference layers give a mechanism for pointing from an NXT
data graph into some data external to NXT that is not in NXT's data
format.  In an external reference layer, the nodes point both
to other NXT nodes and specify a reference to external data.
For instance, an external reference layer might contain annotations
that pair transcribed words with references in an ontology represented
in OWL.  
   </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
   <term>Coding</term>
   <listitem><para> 

A coding is a sequence of one or more layers that describe an
observation, all either for the same agent or for the interaction as a
whole, where each layer’s children are taken from the next layer in
the sequence, ending either in a layer with no children or in a layer
whose children are in the top layer of another coding.  Codings
defined in this way consist of tree structures, and the relations
among codings allow the intersecting hierarchies of the NITE Object
Model. Since most coherent annotations applied to linguistic data fit
into tree structures, for many corpora, the codings will correspond to
what can be thought of loosely as types of annotation.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
   <term>Corpus Resource</term>
   <listitem><para> 
A corpus resource is a sequence of one of more layers that provide
reference data to which coding nodes can point.  A corpus resource
might be used, for instance, to represent the objects in the universe
to which references refer, the lexical entries that correspond to 
spoken word tokens, or an ontology of types for a linguistic phenomena
that provides more information than the basic strings given in a node's
simple type.  The nodes in a corpus resource will not have timing
information. For backwards compatibility, NXT corpora may describe
individual corpus resources as <firstterm>object sets</firstterm> or <firstterm>ontologies</firstterm>, where object sets are expected to form 
flat lists and ontologies may have tree structure. 
   </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
   <term>Code</term>
   <listitem><para> A code is an individual data item, corresponding
   to one node in the NITE Object Model.  The metadata declaration for
   codes of a specific type defines the attribute-value pairs that are
   allowed for that type.  If the code relates to other codes using
   pointers, the declaration specifies by role in which layer the
   target of the pointer must be found.  Further restrictions on the
   types allowed as children for any given code arise from the layer
   in which the code is placed.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>
<para>
Together, these definitions preserve the ordering properties that we
desire; intuitively, time-aligned and structural layers are ordered,
and timings can percolate up structural layers from a time-aligned
layer at the base.  The layer structure within a coding prohibits
cycles. 
</para>

<para> The structure of any particular data set
   is declared in these terms in the metadata file for the 
    corpus and imposed by it; for instance, 
    if you validate a corpus against the
    metadata, any nodes that violate the layering constraints
    declared in the metadata will be
    flagged.  However, technically speaking, the NITE Object Model
    itself is perfectly happy to load and work with data that violates
    the layer model as long as the data graph itself contains no
    cycles.  A number of previous corpora have violated the layering
    model deliberately in order to avoid what the designers see as too
    rigid constraints (see <xref linkend="skiplayers"
endterm="skiplayers.title"/>).  We don't
    recommend this because violations can have unintended consequences
    unless the designers understand how NXT's loading, validation, and
    serialization work, and may not continue to have the same effects
    as NXT development continues.
    </para>
</section>
