<section id="playmedia" xreflabel="How to Play Media in NXT">
    <title>How to Play Media signals in NXT</title>


<para> 
NXT plays media using <ulink
url="http://java.sun.com/products/java-media/jmf/"><package>JMF</package>
(the Java Media Framework)</ulink>.  <package>JMF</package>'s support
for media formats is limited and it depends on the platform you are
using. A list of <package>JMF</package> supported formats is at <ulink
url="http://java.sun.com/products/java-media/jmf/2.1.1/formats.html">
http://java.sun.com/products/java-media/jmf/2.1.1/formats.html</ulink>.
This list is for <package>JMF 2.1.1</package>, which NXT currently
ships with.
</para>

<para>
There are several ways of improving the coverage of
<package>JMF</package> on your platform:

<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
<listitem><para>
Performance packs from <orgname>Sun</orgname> - these improve codec coverage for Windows and Linux, and are available from the 
<ulink url="http://java.sun.com/products/java-media/jmf/2.1.1/download.html"><package>JMF</package> download page</ulink>.
In particular, note that MPEG format isn't supported in the cross-platform version of <package>JMF</package>, but it is in the performance packs.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
<package>Fobs4JMF</package> for Windows / Linux / MacOSX is a very useful package providing Java wrappers for the 
<ulink url="http://ffmpeg.sourceforge.net/index.php">ffmpeg libraries</ulink> 
(C libraries used by many media players which have a <ulink url="http://ffmpeg.sourceforge.net/ffmpeg-doc.html#SEC16">
wide coverage of codecs and formats</ulink>). <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/fobs/">Download</ulink>; 
<ulink url="http://fobs.sourceforge.net/features.html">information</ulink>. 
Make sure you follow the full <ulink url="http://fobs.sourceforge.net/documentation.html">installation instructions</ulink>
 which involve updating the JMFRegistry and amending your <envar>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</envar>. 
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
MP3 - There's an MP3 plugin available for all platforms from <orgname>Sun</orgname>.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
<note>
<para>direct playback from DVDs or CDs is not supported by <package>JMF</package>.</para>
</note>

<para>
NXT comes with a cross-platform distribution of <package>JMF</package>
in the <filename class="directory">lib</filename> directory, and the
<filename class="extension">.bat/.sh</filename> scripts that launch
the GUI samples have this copy of <package>JMF</package> on the
classpath. On a Windows machine, it is better to install
<package>JMF</package> centrally on the machine and change the
<filename class="extension">.bat</filename> script to refer to this
installation.  This will often get rid of error messages and
exceptions (although they don't always affect performance), and allows
<package>JMF</package> to find more codecs.
</para>

<para>
It is a good idea to produce a sample signal and test it in NXT (and
any other tools you intend to use) before starting recording proper,
since changing the format of a signal can be confusing and
time-consuming. There are two tests that are useful.  The first is
whether you can view the signal at all under any application on your
machine, and the second is whether you can view the signal from
NXT. The simplest way of testing the latter is to name the signal as
required for one of the sample data sets in the NXT download and try
the <interface>generic display</interface> or some other tool that
uses the signal.  For video, if the former works and not the latter,
then you may have the video codec you need, but NXT can't find it - it
may be possible to fix the problem by adding the video codec to the
JMF Registry. If neither works, the first thing to look at is whether
or not you have the video codec you need installed on your
machine. Another common problem is that the video is actually OK, but
the header written by the video processing tool (if you performed a
conversion) isn't what <package>JMF</package> expects.  This suggests
trying to convert in a different way, although some brave souls have
been known to modify the header in a text editor.
</para>

<subsection id="macmedia" xreflabel="Media on the Mac">
    <title>Media on the Mac</title>
<para>
NXT ships with some startup scripts for the Mac platform (these are
the .command files) that attempt to use <ulink
url="http://fmj-sf.net/"><package>FMJ</package></ulink> to pass
control of media playing from JMF to the native codecs used by the
<package>Quicktime</package> player. 
</para>

<para>
If the FMJ approach fails, you should still be able to play media on
your Mac but you'll need to edit your startup script. Take an existing
command file as a template and change the classpath. It should contain
<directory>lib/JMF/lib</directory> (so jmf.properties is picked up);
<file>lib/JMF/lib/jmf.jar</file> and
<file>lib/fmj/lib/jffmpeg-1.1.0.jar</file>, but none of the other FMJ
files. This approach uses JFFMPEG more directly and works on some Mac
platforms where the default FMJ approach fails. It may become the
default position for NXT in future.
</para>
</subsection>
</section> 


